build me an app. You can type that into
the new Claude Fable model, and you can
be pretty impressed off the bat. Now,
Anthropic just dropped this new class of
model. It's actually the Claude Mythos
model, but they're calling it Claude
Fable. And apparently, it's safer, I
think. So, my feed this week is full of
people oneshotting video games and
making perfect clones of Slack and
Notion with a single prompt using Claude
Fable. And yeah, it's genuinely
impressive. I mean, the benchmarks are
calling it a real step change above
models like Opus, but you know, I've
never been able to judge a new model
just by toy demos on X or YouTube. The
real test is what it does for our actual
work. So, today I'm putting Fable to
work on a real tool that my business
actually needs, and you'll get to ride
along. So, by the end of this video,
I'll help you figure out how to judge
this new class of AI models that are
just coming out now. And also, we'll
break down when this Claude Fable model
is even worth reaching for because this
thing is expensive. So, here's the real
gap that I'm trying to fill with what
I'm building here today. You know, I
want to be a better teacher on this
channel, but currently the only way that
I'm able to keep a pulse on which topics
actually matter to you is just from me
like scrolling Twitter and scrolling my
YouTube feed. So, I miss some really
good topics that I could teach and cover
here. What I want to build is a kind of
radar system, like something that can
watch the feeds and the sources that I
care about and surface topics that are
climbing in popularity. Now, it's a good
thing that I'm building this today
because as of June 22nd, so less than 2
weeks from now, Claude Fable will no
longer be available under the Cloud Max
subscription plans. So, after that,
you're paying for API tokens. And Fable
is hungry about twice as much what Opus
costs. So if you're on the Max plan and
you have something real that you want to
build with Fable, right now is the time
to try it out. You know, when I show you
my real projects that I'm building in my
business, like I'm doing today, what I
really want you to take away from this
is to help you start to look at your own
business differently. You know, look for
the gaps. Look for the busy work or the
tools that you wish existed or were too
expensive to custom build before.
Because building your own tools and
agents is now within reach. And I don't
mean just for developers. I mean anyone.
You don't have to be technical. Now, of
course, you can't just say, "Build me an
app." And expect it to get it right. I
mean, Claude Fable will impress you. It
might even shock you in what it's
actually capable of, but that doesn't
mean that it will inherently know what
you need or what your business actually
needs out of your tools. So, you or me
as the human in the loop, our role in
this process is in that early planning
and shaping phase. and that is more
important than ever. So, as always,
that's the approach that I'm taking with
the tool that I'm building today. Now,
with Cloud Fable as the workhorse, let's
go. Now, actually, what I'm building
today isn't an entirely new app. I've
already built an app called Residents
Radar, and I've been using this to
organize all of the new ideas that me
and my AI agents pitched to me for me to
kind of review and greenlight them into
development, into topics that I might
share here on YouTube or in my
newsletter. And so, what we're going to
be building here today with the help of
Claude Fable is a major expansion of
this app that I use for curating and
planning out new ideas. So, as you can
see, I already have it set up to sort of
extract potential content ideas from a
variety of sources. And this is kind of
the UI of where I manage sources. But,
as you can see, the sources that I
currently pull from or my agents pull
from when they're pitching ideas to me
come from like my interviews with
customers, logs from my daily work. It
takes a look at the content that I
already publish like in my newsletter,
my tweets, my YouTube videos
and other survey responses from my
audience. So all of this stuff is very
internal facing. So now we need to build
out an external
engine for monitoring and
keeping a pulse on what's happening in
this space of building with AI. So my
starting point for any major expansion
of an app or when I'm planning out a new
app is to actually go into cloud.ai and
this is where I spend a lot of time
doing very high level exploration and
planning and trying out ideas and seeing
how I think how I feel about them and
thinking through them and then
backtracking and doing a lot of back and
forth before I have a really firm
scope and spec. I do it all here in
claw.a AI. So earlier today, what I did
was I started with a pretty long sort of
brain dump. This is just a raw getting
my ideas out. I spoke into the editor
here just some like specific
requirements for exactly how I'm going
to need a tool like this to work in my
workflow and make it work for my
business. So I have some ideas for this
going in. And then I went through a long
back and forth with Claude. So, this
took me, you know, more than half a day
to really go back and forth. And as you
can see, what we're doing is we're not
building the actual plan yet. We're
making decisions together. So, this is
me using Claude as a thought partner, as
a as a strategic planner as I think
through a major tool expansion and
something that I'm building here. So, we
looked at different things like what's
going to go into the UI and the UX, but
also some preliminary technical research
into what's actually possible for us to
pull information from the YouTube API. I
want to pull information off of like X,
you know, Twitter feeds and I was
exploring LinkedIn and Reddit to see if
I can pull ideas from those sorts of
feeds to understand what are the
trending topics in these platforms. What
are the top questions that people in the
audience have and these are things that
potentially I could talk about and teach
here on the channel. Again, we went
through a long back and forth just
hashing it out. And for most of this, I
was actually using the new Claude Fable
model. And that is available here in the
Claude model picker, but as you can see,
there's this caveat that it's included
until June 22nd. So, as of today, I'm
recording this on June 10th. That's like
less than 2 weeks away. So, I better get
my Fable usage in now before it runs
out. So, we kept going. As you can see,
this is a really long one. They tend to
be pretty long when we're planning out a
new product. My output from this session
is this artifact. So I'm always kind of
building toward a usable artifact. This
is not quite what I would consider to be
a PRD. This is more like a really
extensive initial prompt that I'm going
to copy and paste into Claude code in
just a minute. So this is kind of like
locking in all of the decisions that me
and Claude made together in this in this
planning session. we sort of lock them
in and codify them into this scoping
document. I specifically asked Claude to
try to avoid being too prescriptive on
like how to code this up, how to
actually implement it. This is more
about defining the scope, what we are
going to be building here, what we're
not building, what we're going to be
integrating with, and a couple of other
like important points here. There is a
little bit of database modeling here.
Again, it's pretty high level. So like
establishing some new entities that
we're going to be adding into my
application. Now one of the most
important pieces in this in this
document here is this final section
verification criteria definition of
done. So
this is becoming a really important
pattern in how we spec and plan and give
AI models especially the really powerful
ones like Claude Fable. How do we get
give them these initial instructions or
our initial request and give them a set
of criteria like literally a checklist
here that it can use to define done
because I'm just going to let Claude
Fable you know cook on this and it's
going to go and instead of my usual
thing which is to break it up into you
know smaller buildable chunks I'm going
to see if it can actually build all of
this and as it goes it can use this as
its verification to really selfch
checkck back and self- test and that's
when it knows it'll be done and we'll
see how far we go with it. So now I have
something that I can actually copy and
paste into cloud code and that's what
we're going to do here in just a sec.
Hey, real quick. If you're new here, I'm
Brian Castle. I help builders stay ahead
of the curve as building with AI becomes
the norm. If this is the kind of thing
that you want to build yourself, I teach
a course called Become the Builder. It's
the missing on-ramp for building real
apps with AI, even if you've never coded
before. So, we cover the foundations,
the tech stack, the templates, and
you'll build and ship your first real
app. That's inside of Builder Methods
Pro. That's where you'll get access to
all my courses along with our community
of builders. So, you can join us by
going to buildermethods.com/pro.
I hope to see you in there. Okay, so we
have this shaped up scoping document
from my conversation with Claude. I'm
going to copy that and then I'm going to
hop into cloud code. So here we are in
cloud code. As you can see I am running
the fable 5 model currently with high
effort and once again we have the
announce this little announcement from
anthropic that fable model is here and
it's included in my plan my claude max
subscription plan until June 22nd. So I
better start building now. Now I'm
currently on the main branch. So So I'm
actually going to spin up a new work
tree for this. So now I'm actually
operating in a new work tree. By the
way, I've been jumping around different
apps for managing agents in different
work trees. Today I'm using one called
Superconductor, which I really like so
far. It's really nice interface,
especially if you're doing, you know,
multiple work trees, multiple agents
across multiple projects like I tend to
do. Anyway, so here we are. Now, as an
experiment, I want to see if I could
sort of skip ahead and skip a few steps
that I would normally otherwise do in my
building workflow. So, normally I would
take this shaped up document and I would
bring it into cloud code, but from there
I would then turn it into more of a
formal PRD or product requirements
document, which is sort of like a
buildable road map. And actually, I have
a free agent skill that you can plug
into Cloud Code or any agent called PRD
Creator. And I covered that in depth in
a video on the channel just a couple
weeks ago. That skill is available at
their methods.com/prdcreator.
So, this is what I normally use these
days to plan out a new build. I would
take my scoping document or a raw
initial prompt and it would turn it into
a PRD and then actually break it out
into multiple milestones and then I
would feed each milestone into cloud
code. And I would also run plan mode on
cloud code to really have it plan out
the implementation and kind of go one
piece at a time. And that's how I tend
to like to build. it probably still will
continue to build that way, but today I
want to be a little bit more ambitious
and just really put Claude Fable to the
test. So, I'm just going to go ahead and
paste that shaping document in as is.
And I'm just going to add one more
thing. And I'm going to say here, that's
what we're building today. I want you to
ask me any clarifying questions about
the implementation before you get
started.
So, let's see how Fable does with asking
me clarifying questions, which I think
is always a really important step in the
process. Now, by the way, again,
normally I would probably use like plan
mode for something like this. Might even
use the new goal feature in Cloud Code
since this is going to be a pretty big
project for it to bite off, but I kind
of want to just see how it works. Just,
you know, plain old Cloud Code. Drop a
huge prompt in there. See how we go.
Now, as you can see, this is not, you
know, just a thin build me an app
prompt. You know, I really spent a lot
of time in cloud code like hashing out
exactly what I want to build. So,
there's a lot in here, a lot of detail,
and it's going to analyze what I already
have in my resonance radar application.
So, I expect that it'll have some
questions. And this is one of those
things that I like to evaluate a new
model to see what kind of questions to
see how constructive and thoughtful they
are to see what it comes back with
because again that pattern of you know
telling the agent to ask you clarifying
questions or to interview you or to
grill you that's a really important
pattern because it helps shape your
thinking. It helps shape your planning
and that's how we kind of transition
from just being a vibe coder to being a
professional builder. That's what this
is all about. So this is pretty typical
these days. I've noticed this with Opus
as well. When it gets started on a big
exploration of a codebase or really big,
you know, prompting request, it will
actually spin off multiple sub agents
automatically. And you can you can
literally see that down here. So this is
like the main agent and then over here
it's doing like an exploration of the
codebase. So normal stuff. It's thinking
it's checking things out. Okay. So, that
initial exploration that took about a
minute 40 seconds, 58,000.
And here are a couple of clarifying
questions that it's asking me. And I'm
just going to get these answered for
Claude. These are pretty good questions
so far. Ah, it caught a little detail
that I forgot to provide it earlier. All
right. So, you know, it's finding little
details that I sort of overlooked or
kind of had the wrong information in my
original shaping document. So, this is
really good. it it's actually catching
some things that I think Opus probably
wouldn't have caught to be honest. It
correctly notices like what my
infrastructure is in my Rails
application, what kind of background job
system I have working and it's going to
incorporate that into some of the logic.
So that's good as well. By the way, I
already put in place my YouTube API
credentials for the agent to be able to
access. And another note, I didn't
mention this earlier, I'm following a
very similar pattern that I'm using in
almost all my apps these days. And I
covered this in a previous video called
the night shift model where I build a
custom application like resonance radar,
which is sort of the UI layer and the
API layer. And then I have AI agents,
whether it's cloud code or my Hermes
agent or cloud co-work be able to run on
recurring schedules. and that and those
are what do the actual thinking and
creative work and then they read and
post data and information back to these
custom apps. So that's what we're going
to be doing here. And as part of that
shaping document, it was which was it
was sort of buried in there.
We're instructing Claude to work on both
expanding the feature set of resonance
radar the application as well as
building out some new agent skills that
I'm going to assign to my agents running
on a daily recurring schedule. Okay, so
I can see here that Claude is now
starting to just go ahead and get
started right now. Again, I didn't do
the typical plan mode, which usually
kind of shows me the plan and then gives
me like a a confirmation to yes, go
ahead and get started. since I just
started in regular, you know, prompt
mode, it's just going to go ahead and
get started and it's creating it has
created a to-do list for itself. So,
yeah, we're going to just kind of let it
cook here and let's see how we go. Okay,
so it's all set and let's see how it
did. So, it made this final report and
you know, this reads pretty typical from
a typical like final report when I'm
using Opus. I would say the writing is a
bit tighter and easier for me to quickly
get a grasp on what was built. So, I
like that. I noticed down here it said
that it crunched for about 41 minutes. I
think that might have included some of
the early planning as well. All right,
so let's actually run the server and see
we're how we're doing. So, I'm still
like running this locally. This is with
like seated fake data in here. So, I can
already see that it added a bunch of
stuff to the navigation. So, we have a
watch list. So these are like new
sources.
So we have the original sources over
here and then we also have these like
external sources. Later on I might want
to like merge these into the same area,
but more of a design decision that I
might make later like now that I'm
looking at it. So yeah, like a bunch of
like random YouTube channels and Reddit
subreddits that we've sort of like
preeded in here. And each like channel
or subreddit has some has some like
details like what kind of platform it is
and the feed URL. Okay, that's looking
good. All right, so here is the list of
like trending topics that it's sort of
extracting from these from the sources
from the watch list. Now, I don't know
if these are actually real. Let's see.
View original. This is actually not
correct. Like it's not even the same
topic. And I'm also not really seeing
any other content other than this. So I
don't know if this might be just like a
fake seated piece of content because
we're in the local development
environment. I'm going to ask Claude
about that. One other thing that I'm
noticing like now that I'm looking at
it. So it did build out like the
algorithm if you will for how we
calculate how much a topic is trending,
right? Like the magnitude of from the
source norm. That's a little bit
confusing, but I know what it means.
It's like how much this is trending from
how of like what a typical topic within
this subreddit would do and like the
velocity. So how much time goes by
before it gets to this level of
popularity.
But the way that we're displaying this
stuff is a little bit confusing. So
yeah, those two issues. Let's go back
and ask the model, you know, what we can
do about these things. So again, this is
like one more test of like how it
handles feedback and this kind of
refinements loop. So let's just do one
quick round here. I noticed that the
trending topics that are shown don't
seem to link to real posts. They don't
seem to be found on YouTube and Reddit
and X. Are these dummy fake data records
or are these supposed to link out to
real posts that actually live on the
internet? Then, you know, sometimes I
like to like batch my quick feedback
like this and take a screenshot of that.
Also noticing that these stats for
magnitude and velocity and the outlier
score, I get what they mean, but they're
a little bit confusing. Can we make
these simpler and especially have some
visual indication for how
these stats compare to the norm or like
a I don't know like a visual graph or
heat tracker. I don't know something
like that. And let's take a look at the
reports. So here is a report. We've got
a couple of featured items and we have
some content here. So that's pretty
good. But I would have expected the
padding on this to be a little bit
cleaner. So I guess it didn't really
catch that. Let's have it clean that up.
The padding on this report content needs
to be cleaned up. The text is currently
butdding up against the border. All
right. So I'm going to let the
model turn on that for a minute.
Now, of course, a lot of this stuff
could have been a result of kind of
giving it overly specific instructions
in my original shaping document. That
could have been a risk that I ran here.
And also, also, you know, again, I
skipped through my typical process,
which takes a little bit more of a
stepped approach with a proper PRD and
breaking it up into milestones. You
know, something like this, we probably
would have built in like two or three
different milestones. So that's my
normal process when I take a more
methodical like hands-on approach. The
other thing is like since we're building
into an existing application, an
existing codebase, that can always be a
little bit tricky, but you know, I
wanted to kind of put Fable to the test
here. Let's see how it's doing. Okay, so
actually those were dummy records that I
created purely just to verify the UI. So
I think that those actually weren't
bugs. It it's really just I you know,
those aren't expected to link out to
real posts. Yeah. So that's something
that I'll verify like once we get this
deployed onto production. Okay. So it
worked on that for about 7 minutes. A
little slow for kind of like quick
turnarounds like this. But you know I
don't expect this to be a very fast
model. Yeah. So let's see how it did.
Yeah. These are actually much better.
More visual and the content of how they
work here seems to make a little bit
more sense. I might massage it a little
bit more once I start to use it
dayto-day. That'll be like the real test
for like how useful this stuff is,
especially when I'm looking at this data
and using it in my real process in my
business. But that's definitely an
improvement. And let's see how it did
with the report. Yeah, it just cleaned
that up. So, yeah, that's good to go.
So, look, we're in the earliest days of
getting to know Claude Fable. I mean,
clearly it is a step change in
capability, but we'll see what kind of
impact it has in the coming months. For
now, I do have two observations that we
should keep our eye on. So observation
one, that refinement stage is starting
to melt away. You know, for the past
year, my whole process has been spec
driven. Shape a clear plan, build, and
then refine. And that refinement stage,
you know, rounds of back and forth after
that first build, that's always been a
real chunk of work. But with Fable, I
think that part is starting to
disappear. Not the planning. The
planning matters as much as ever, maybe
even more. It's the fixing and the
reprompting. The No, not like that. that
stuff is reducing since Fable seems to
be really good at checking its own work
as long as you give it clear notes on
what done looks like. You know that
verification criteria. So that brings me
to observation number two. Choosing the
right model is now the new skill because
this capability is expensive and it's
about to get even more expensive after
June 22nd because Cloud Fable is not
going to be covered under the Claude Max
plan after that time at least right now.
So the question isn't just can the model
build this. Now it's a question of is
this the job that's worth pointing fable
at. So I think we're going to start to
see a divergence of what we think of as
our daily driver models. I mean for me
that's still opus but now we also have
these heavy hitter models like claude
fable where we can use them in select
cases for really big important jobs.
Now, being able to leverage AI tools and
the best in-class models like Claude
Fable is pretty incredible, but only if
you're able to plan like a professional
builder. The good news is that planning
skill and the building skill is
learnable even if you've never written a
line of code. So, I made a whole video
walking through exactly how I take a raw
idea and shape it into a plan that's
ready to build with the same attention
to detail that an experienced software
designer would bring. So, you can go
watch that next. But before you do, hit
subscribe so you don't miss my next
video on building with AI. And then I'll
see you over there next.